I think it's understandable to be
cautious or even dismissive of
supplements. Many have little to no good
quality evidence behind them. But
fascinatingly, we have a brand new
randomized control trial on cancer and
how a supplement actually helps prevent
cancer. And in fact, the initial study
released several years ago, but I don't
actually don't remember it getting many
headlines. Now, however, a follow-up
study has been published in a big
journal, Cell Reports Medicine. Now, the
supplement is bourbon, a naturally
occurring molecule extracted from the
barberry plant. So, what can we take
away from this study? And I'll actually
go ahead and tell you there's something
pretty remarkable about this supplement
captured in the second study that I'll
tell you about. Initially, we I mean
scientists looked at bourberine by
conducting a randomized control trial by
including almost 1,000 participants
randomly assigned to consume bourberine
in pill form twice a day or an identical
looking pill that did not contain
bourberine called the placebo. Now both
groups were instructed to keep taking
their respective pills for 2 years. Now,
the outcome of interest was the
development of adenomomas, meaning
precancerous abnormal growth in the
colon. These aren't guaranteed to grow
into cancer, but they are much more
likely because they share some, though
not all of the characteristics of
cancer. Looking at the data, you can
focus on the graph for simplicity. The
black dotted line is the comparison
line. If anything touches it, it means
that the result is not statistically
significantly identified to have an
effect. Now, if it moves to the left,
there is an effect detected. I don't
need to spell it out more than that. The
Bourberine group clearly experienced
fewer adenomas than the placebo over the
2 years of Bourberine consumption. This
was confirmed in a variety of different
ways. Ultimately, we're looking at a 23%
reduced risk. The point here is that
bourberin directly protects against
precancerous growth forming in the
colon. But it doesn't stop there because
there are also severities of cancer
progression. Now you've probably heard
of stages one, two, three, and four for
cancers. They describe severity. Now in
colon cancer, looking at adenomomas,
the size, the shape, the color, the
structure determines if it's advanced or
non-advanced. So the question is, does
bourberine help reduce the severity of
what gross do form? The answer is again
yes. In fact almost 50% though the exact
number is a bit in the air considering
what are known as confidence intervals
but based on these data yes a near 50%
reduction in advanced adenomomas. This
of course follows through with the
non-advanced as well because the overall
risk was reduced as we went over. Now,
we're talking about bourbon not only
being protective overall against
precancerous lesions, but also reduces
the severity of whatever lesions might
still appear. Remarkable. Now, that's
all pretty impressive, right? Like I
mentioned, there's plenty of room for
skepticism around supplements, but here
we're getting some pretty solid proof
that something that we don't normally
engage with may provide some benefit.
But what if I told you this first study
isn't even the most impressive? The most
impressive lies in this follow-up study
and is all beautifully illustrated in
this one image.
But before that, aren't you the least
bit curious on exactly how bourberin
does this? Are we absorbing bourberin
and then it launches rockets at
precancerous cells? Is it befriending
cancer cells and then stabbing them as
they yell, "Hey, to Brutus."
I like to think that, but that's
probably not what's happening. Now,
what's been proposed is that common
tumores pathways, which means
cancerromoting pathways within our
cells, are inhibited by bourberine. So
as bourberine is absorbed by these
colonocytes, these colon cells, it
interacts with proteins in our cells,
preventing the signals from pushing
procancerous.
Even outside the cell, bourbon is
believed to change the microbiome by
changing the microbiome environment,
possibly making it less hospitable place
for colurectal cancer to grow. Now, I'd
actually like to touch on this a little
bit later again because I could envision
a scenario where bourberine is
ineffective for many people. Now, in
short, bourberine is proposed to work
directly at inhibiting cancer cell
growth and indirectly by promoting an
anti-cancerous gut microbiome. So, we've
been going over the general effects of
bourbon and cancer prevention,
and there's much more in different
subgroups like the effects based on age,
history of cancer, other health issues,
severity of adenomomas, and more. I'm
covering that in the extended version of
this video that you're watching along
with supplement recommendations. If
you're interested in access to it, plus
all my work in video, written and audio
form, all ad free, plus all these perks
like live sessions with me and the
community, get access by becoming a
physionic insider. It helps me continue
my work here, and it's a wealth of
information broken down into actionable
steps and additional nuances. The link
to join is in the description box. Hope
to see you there. Now, to this second
study, I'll keep this as simple as I
can. This is a followup on a randomized
control trial that we covered. That
means most of the same participants were
enrolled and assessed years later after
the study conclusion. So 6 years to be
exact. Now I'm going to show you the
graph again and then I'm going to drop a
bombshell on you. A good bombshell if
such a thing exists. Here it is. I feel
like I should add angelic music to
accompany as you'll understand shortly.
You can ignore the table with the
numbers. I'm including it for those that
know how to read it. For those more
visually and less numerically crazed,
notice the 1.0 line running
horizontally. That is our baseline risk.
If the squares and lines move down from
that line, there's reduced adenoma
recurrence, as in reduced chance of
adenomomas returning. Each datim is a
different year. The two initial years of
the trial and then six more follow-up
years. You see it right? You do notice
that with every passing year, we get
tighter and tighter data indicating
bourbon continues incredibly to reduce
the risk of these pesky adenomas. So,
this means there is a continued
long-term colon cancer risk reduction.
Pretty striking. But here's the
bombshell. The participants were no
longer consuming bourberin. That's
right. The first two years they were,
but the final six years as risk was
still reduced they weren't. Now that's
an incredible finding. I don't care what
anybody says. So this means that
bourberine consumption associates with
long-term reduced risk of colurectal
cancer even when consumption is stopped
years back. You may have noticed I said
the word associates and that actually
wasn't a slip of the tongue. It's a
deliberate choice of words to indicate
that these data are no longer causitive.
The reason is that because of the length
of the study time, there was no
randomization of the included
participants, though they were
originally randomized and there's no
intervention anymore. I think someone
could argue this is a bit of a quasi
situation where we could make uh some
claims to causation, but there's plenty
of space there for other influencing
factors. Now to be fair, the researchers
did account for many influencing
factors. So all these data are certainly
exciting. We have good quality evidence
that bourberin works here. But I did
mention there might be one pause to the
excitement.
If we think back to one of the main
proposed mechanisms of action and
considering the long-standing effects,
it is entirely possible that people who
already have a healthy microbiome may
not experience benefit from bourberine.
The participant pool was entirely
Chinese, so nutrition style may play a
role in the effectiveness since
nutrition is a heavy player in changing
our microbiome. Would this apply to
European cultural foods or African?
Would it apply to people consuming a
ketogenic diet, a plant dominant diet?
We don't know that yet. Another
limitation, though not as serious in my
mind, is the fact that these studies
focus on people with adenomomas in their
past and have been removed. So would
this still apply in people without
issues with their colon? We don't know
that yet. These data are not exclusive
to people with colctal cancer past. But
they may not be representative of a
healthy population either, which may
also speak to my first point further.
What we do know is that accepting these
limitations, 600 mgs of bourberine split
into two doses was effective at
protecting against colurectal cancer
linked gross with a need for more
studies to confirm these results by
other researchers, other studies in
different groups of people and so on. So
where does that leave you? First, we saw
good evidence that bourbon protects
against the number and severity of
precancerous growth in the colon. This
effect may be longstanding, continuing
for five or more years, even when no
longer consuming bourberine. As for what
to do, well, that depends. There were
few side effects from bourberine
supplementation across these studies.
And if you have a history of abnormal
growth in the colon, it may be worth
trying verber. Now, if you do not have a
history of colctal cancer, there's no
data here that offers definitive
evidence for you. But it wouldn't
surprise me if this translated to people
without a history of precancerous
growth. So it may be worth a shot, too.
The dose used was 600 mg per day. If
you're interested in independently
tested supplements, I offer a list that
I'm not affiliated with in my Physionic
Insider subscription. Keep in mind that
this is still early days, but certainly
nothing to ignore, even if we need more
data to confirm and learn some of the
additional nuances. There's some
additional work that I've done on the
benefits of bourberine which I cover
right here too. Or if you're interested
in cancer prevention directly, there's a
powerful way simply consuming more of
this nutrient. Of course, I can't tell
you what that nutrient is. That would
spoil the fun. Thanks for tuning in. I
appreciate it and I'll catch you in the
next one. Bye.